<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Animadversions upon a fatal period, or, A brief discourse concerning the present state of the body, and the future state of the soul by Tho. Collard.</title>
            <author>Collard, Tho.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1678</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 103 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 52 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B08795</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C5102A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R174032</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">61296941</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 61296941</idno>
            <idno type="VID">180513</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B08795)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 180513)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2832:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Animadversions upon a fatal period, or, A brief discourse concerning the present state of the body, and the future state of the soul by Tho. Collard.</title>
                  <author>Collard, Tho.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 83, [5] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.D. for Thomas Basset,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1678.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes advertisements at end -- [5] p.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Eschatology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:180513:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:180513:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>ANIMADVERSIONS UPON A FATAL PERIOD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Or, a Brief DISCOURSE Concerning The Preſent State of the Body, And The Future State of the Soul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> Tho. Collard, <hi>M. A.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>O Jeruſalem, Jeruſalem, thou that killeſt the Prophets, and stonest them which are ſent unto thee, how often would I have gathered thy children together, even as an hen ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereth her chickens under her wings, and ye would not? <bibl>
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 23. 37.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, <hi>Printed by</hi> T. D. <hi>for</hi> Thomas Baſſet <hi>at the</hi> George <hi>near St.</hi> Dunſtans <hi>Church in</hi> Fleet-ſtreet. 1678.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:180513:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:180513:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the judicious, knowing, and skilful Phyſicians, Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries, and Chirurgians:</hi> Theſe Animadverſions upon a fatal Period, are moſt humbly dedicated by the Author.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured Sirs,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Hope I may beg, and eaſily obtain your pardon, for prefixing your names to theſe few Sheets; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your whole Profeſſion, by the clearest Conſequence, is, by ſome mens endeavours, likely to be defam'd and caſhier'd, as one great Imposture.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:180513:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:180513:3"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <p>THe Notion of a Deſtiny, of the Fatal Event of all things, of peremptory and abſolute Decrees, being once im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bibed by the Vulgar, or even by their great Abettors; they ſoon commence ſuch excellent Sophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters as to argue and cajole them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves out of all morality and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty: Abold and Hectoring
<pb facs="tcp:180513:4"/> confidence, an idle and fruitleſs faith, Yeas and Nays, grave nods, ſadtones and accents, wrie Mouths, ſullen and lugubrious looks, Hypocriſie and meer For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malities with the more <hi>precious</hi> Sort of them; and oaths, cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, imprecations, and notorious frolicks and debaucheries with the <hi>Prophaner:</hi> have the like influence (they think) on God, concerning their preſent and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture State; as truth, ſincerity, temperance, ardent zeal, emient piety, real charity and devotion. For the Almighty, in their judgments, before they had a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:180513:4"/> deſign'd their Fate either of bliſs or miſery, which neither Vice nor Virtue can alter.</p>
            <p>Death 'tis confest, is very formidous, of a tragical and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtere Aſpect, and Life, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally eternal, is ſweet and eligible, deſir'd and courted by all; but ſhould they endeavour to uſe all the Means and Methods ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable to eſchew the One, and to enjoy the Other; yet a previ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and dormant Decree might frustrate their deſigns, and preſs them to the infernal Pit, whiles, Ideots like, they were aſpiring for Heaven. This ſuperſedes their
<pb facs="tcp:180513:5"/> care and industry, makes them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect an extravagant Romance, a Dithyrambick, or a hymn of their own making, as good for the Health of their Souls, as the whole Duty of Man, <hi>Te Deum,</hi> or one of Davids Penitentials; and Chalk Aſhes, and Sawdust as efficacious for the Health of their Bodyes, as the richeſt Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lips and Cordials; and ſo Both oftentimes periſh either by Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption or Deſpair: theſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the direful Effects and ſad reſults, which naturally iſſue, like inſipid rivulets from putrid ſprings, from ſuch brain-ſick and vertiginous Phancies.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:180513:5"/>
            <p> There are many (I know) ela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borate and judicious Diſcourſes, both from the Preſs and the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit, which ſince the bleſſed and miraculous Restauration of our exil'd <hi>KING</hi> and <hi>CHURCH,</hi> have like ſo many holy Engines batter'd down thoſe prodigious Opinions concerning Gods most just and ſacred Decrees: Yet the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagion ſtill remaining in theſe Parts, as was evident from W. C's Pulpit-Prate in Vindicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a Fatal Period, and the Turks Aphoriſm, <hi>Quod termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus vitae eſt immutabilis;</hi> and even as it now appears from the
<pb facs="tcp:180513:6"/> Preſs in its new form, after two years licking: (for there are ſome things added, as that of Bp. H. and more omitted;) yet the zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Harangue is still a Bear, able to ſtartle all that have any good thoughts of a Deity, or any real eſtimate for Truth, Reaſon, Piety, Religion, and the Sincerity of the Sacred Writ<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> tho 'tis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd by his infatuated Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lytes with as great veneration, as one of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtles. And this is no Novelty nor wonder neither: for 'tis storied of a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neva Innocent (I might ſay a blaſphemous Zealot) that ſaid,
<pb facs="tcp:180513:6"/> 
               <hi>Si veniret Sanctus Paulus qui eadem horâ concionaretur quâ &amp; Calvinus, ego relicto Paulo audirem Calvinum,</hi> If St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſhould come from Heaven, and Preach at the ſame time that Calvin did; I would deſert <hi>Paul,</hi> and attend and hear precious Mr. <hi>John Calvin.</hi> Compariſons (I know) are odious; and I muſt needs confeſs, that there is as vaſt a difference between <hi>J. C.</hi> the Master, and <hi>W. C.</hi> the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, as there is between a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile Politician that can Argue and Rhetoricate, and one of his talkative Bigots.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:180513:7"/>
            <p> Our Plebeans and Artizans, and most that formerly frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the illegal Meetings, being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with the ſowr Leaven of abſolute and irreſpective Decrees of Election and Reprobation, which are us'd by them as Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licons to free them from all the diſeaſes both of body and mind, from all faults and Errors: for after the most detestable acts and hainous offences, they uſually ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace themſelves (as I have often known,) That all was decreed, allotted, and appointed for them: that Gods will muſt be done: and that if God had given them <hi>bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:180513:7"/> 
               <hi>Grace,</hi> (as they uſually word it) they had been better men, and leſs peccant. So that the poor ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant Creatures (tho highly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited of their own, as well as of their Teachers knowledg) dream, that the Almighty is oblig'd in honour to pardon their moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberate and blackeſt crimes; they being (according to their own Principles,) neceſſitated thereto by his own eternal and immuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Act and Deed. This Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagion, I ſay, being yet amongst us: This mean Antidote may not, I preſume, prove altogether ineffectual, tho not totally to Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay
<pb facs="tcp:180513:8"/> and expel, yet in ſome meaſure to put a ſtop to the Increaſe and ſpreading of it; which has been one of the grand Cauſes of that vaſt Empire Sin has got in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland ſince the publick Preaching of it, in (and a little before) our late intestine Commotions. I ſhall not apologize, but ſhall leave the enſuing Lines to thy ſerious and impartial Conſideration.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:180513:8"/>
            <head>A brief Diſcourſe.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Ezek. 18. 31,</bibl>
               <q>Caſt away from you all your tranſgreſſions, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ye have tranſgreſſed, and make you a new heart, and a new ſpirit; for why will ye die, O houſe of Iſrael?</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE many Miſapprehenſions of God, eſpecially concerning the ſecret pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes of his Will, which he neither commands us to ſearch after, nor will permit us to know; (and ſurely then were we but half aſhamed of notorious
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:180513:9"/> Contradictions, we ſhould never pretend to know Gods Decrees, which we call hidden and ſecret;) and the divers Miſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions of the Divine Attributes, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally concerning his Juſtice and Mercy; are none of the ſmalleſt Cauſes of thoſe groſs Errors and ſcandalous practices that are found amongſt the Propugners of them. The Pulpit, Chair, and Preſs, (when we found by woful experience that Maxim verified, <hi>No Biſhop, no King)</hi> inſinuated un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us ſuch Opinions and Doctrines, (one of the moſt blaſphemous that ever I heard, was vented, when the Good Old Cauſe was rampant, by Mr. <hi>W.</hi> at a Soul-edifying Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture; <hi>viz. That we are not ſaved by Jeſus Chriſt.)</hi> as infer falſhood in God, and ſet an oppoſition between his revealed and his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Will, his holy Commands and juſt Decrees, making the one a blind for the better execution of the other; as if all the love and mercy he expreſſes, all the paſſionate invitations he makes were only to mock and delude us. And as ſeveral ills (ſaith the moſt judicious, and ever to be admir'd Author of the Cauſes of the Decay of Chriſtian Piety) are hereby
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:180513:9"/> countenanced and authoriz'd, ſo is all Virtue in general diſcouraged and diſheart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; theſe benumb us in our Chriſtian courſe, ſubſtract that ſpirit and vigour, which ſhould carry us through the weary ſtages of duty: indeed they cut the very ſinews of Induſtry, baffle and make ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous all purpoſes of Labour, the Miniſters Preaching, and the Peoples Hearing and Doing: for what ſhould invite a man to ſtrive for that, from which he knows he is either irreverſibly precluded, or elſe ſo infallibly aſcertain'd of, that his negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence cannot defeat him.</p>
            <p>GOD has given us Rules of Life, which upon the ſevereſt Penalties he requires us to ſtudy and practiſe; and we divert from theſe, and make it our buſineſs to trace his Counſels. We are gazing at the Stars to read our Deſtiny, and look not to our feet; and by that negligence experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the worſt fate they could have por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended: for I think we may ſay our wild Phancies about Gods Decrees, have in event reprobated more than thoſe Decrees, upon which they are ſo willing to charge their ruine, and have bid fair to the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:180513:10"/> of many, whom thoſe left ſalvable. We often forget our Calling by contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plating our Predeſtination; and let the Opinion of our Fate be at once the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement and Excuſe of our ſloth, than which nothing can more evacuate the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and deſign of our Chriſtianity, which Divines have truly defin'd to be not a contemplative but active Science.</p>
            <p>THE Almighty interrogates the houſe of Iſrael, <hi>Why will ye die?</hi> and tells them in the ſubſequent Verſe, <hi>I have no pleaſure in the death of him that dieth; wherefore turn your ſelves, and live ye?</hi> Yet ſome bold In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitors into Gods Decrees and hidden Counſels dream, That his ſecret Will is of a very diſtant nature to his revealed; <hi>Et Deus ita terminum ſeu horam mortis homini praefinierit decreto abſoluto; ut hâc ipsâ horâ, &amp; non aliâ, hoc ipſo mortis genere, quo homo mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritur, &amp; non alio, mori illum ſimpliciter abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſit neceſsarium:</hi> and that the Soul likewiſe is liable to the ſame fatality. That Myriads do what they can, are from Gods eternal and immutable purpoſe ordain'd for death and endleſs miſery; and a very few Favourites only, in compariſon of the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:180513:10"/> reſt, do what they will, are predeſtin'd to life and immortal Glory. This wounds the Credit both of the Divines and the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians, of their Proſelytes and Patients; and by the cleareſt conſequence makes the former Cheats, and the later Fools. But whether true or no, we come now to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider.</p>
            <p>THE Queſtion here, <hi>Why will ye die?</hi> and the Proteſtation, <hi>I have no pleaſure in the death of him that dieth;</hi> may clear Gods ways of being either cruel or unequal; and evidently demonſtrate the Almighty's Philanthropy, and his high reſentment of the ruine and Perdition either of Body or Soul. And firſt concerning the preſent State of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. <note place="margin">The preſent ſtate of the Body.</note>
            </p>
            <p>THE Protoplaſt, had he continued in his integrity, (as he might, for God gave him ſufficient power to ſtand, and did not withdraw the leaſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of his Grace, or infuſe into him any ſecret impulſe or motion, whereby he might deviate from that ſacred ſtation in which he was plac'd;) he had been free from death; but having once eaten the prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:180513:11"/> fruit, 'twas neceſſary by Gods Decree (but not before) that Death ſhould arreſt him for it; for the immutable Creator had ſaid, <hi>That in the day thou eateſt thereof, thou ſhalt ſurely die,</hi> Gen. 2. 17. So that we may not before the Fall (altho it be true ſince) term death, with <hi>Socinus,</hi> to be <hi>naturae ſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la per ſe. For as by Adam Sin enter'd into the world, ſo death by ſin,</hi> Rom. 5. 12. And as it follows; <hi>ſo death paſſed upon all men, for that all have ſinned:</hi> that is, All meer men that were after born, were ſinners, born after the image and likeneſs of <hi>Adam</hi> that was now a ſinner, and had begotten no Child in his innocence. Sinful men then we are all, and die once we muſt by reaſon of our Fore-father's Apoſtaſie. 'Tis true, we read that <hi>Lazarus</hi> and others being raiſed from the dead, without controverſie died twice; but the Author (St. <hi>Paul</hi> doubtleſs) of the <hi>Heb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Chap.</hi> 9. 27. ſpeaks of the natural Law, whereby it is appointed unto all or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily once to die; ſo that 'tis not op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to this truth, becauſe others have died twice, which by an extraordinary manner happen'd only to a few. And as for thoſe that ſhall be found alive at the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:180513:11"/> ſecond and ſudden coming of Chriſt, they ſhall be changed in a moment, and in the twinckling of an eye; which mutation or change ſhall be to them inſtead of death. 'Tis then moſt apparent, that 'tis ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily appointed unto men once to die; and then certainly to come to judgment, to be puniſhed or rewarded according to their actions. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 10. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 10.</p>
            <p>OUR brittle and terreſtrial Bodies, we all grant, muſt be diſſolved; for our Bounds are ſet, and our lives limited within ſuch a number of years, beyond which, by the ordinary courſe of nature we cannot paſs; but our Days are not ſo ſtrictly and fatally limited and determin'd, as if neither God nor man could extend or ſhorten them. The fifteen years added to <hi>Hezekiah</hi>'s days, aſſure us of Gods power to prolong the life of man; and Reaſon, Experience, and all Hiſtory both ſacred and prophane, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim his power to ſhorten it. And thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of Examples too ſadly evince, how expert and indefatigable many are in put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a Period to their own and other mens days, in the midſt and prime of their ſtrength and ſplendor. A man may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:180513:12"/> him<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, his Friend, Neighbour, or Enemy, before he hath ſeen thirty years, that otherwiſe might have ſeen threeſcore. And therefore a fatal Period, in the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all conſidering men, is no leſs than a Stoical, Aſtrological, and Mahometan Dream; or at beſt but a popular Error, as our immortal Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> terms it in his Poſtſcript of new Light.</p>
            <p>AND we likewiſe confeſs, That God does know, and may foretel the very time, manner, and place of any mans death; but 'tis a ſimple Logician, and a giddy and hot-braind Chriſtian, that from Gods Predictions and Revelations of the period of ſome mens lives, as of <hi>Aaron, Paſhur, Hophni</hi> and <hi>Phineas,</hi> and of the holy Jeſus; will hence infer, (as <hi>W. C.</hi> moſt irrationally doth) that therefore the very moment, the very kind, (tho it be ſelf-murther) and place of every mans death, are fatally, and abſolutely decreed and appointed.</p>
            <p>I ſhall tranſcribe our famous Preacher's very expreſſions and words, which indeed would have ſounded better from the mouth of a bold Gladiator, with a Sword in his hand ready for Combat, or from a
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:180513:12"/> Magiſterial Adventurer, than from a <hi>Lover of Humility;</hi> as our great lover of popular applauſe is characteriz'd, and in all humility publickly proclaim'd by his friend and neighbour, his profound Champion; who doubtleſs hath an equal inſpection both into the Law and the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>W. C.</hi> pag. 7. <hi>Death</hi> (as to all the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular circumſtances of it) <hi>is foreappointed and determined by Gods Eternal purpoſe.</hi> 1. <hi>As to the time when a man ſhall dye: It muſt be ſuch a time, ſuch a day, and ſuch a moment. Thus for the time when.</hi> 2, <hi>The next circumſtance</hi> (pag. 10, 11.) <hi>I ſhall ſpeak of is, the place Where we muſt (or if you will, rather where we ſhall) dye;</hi> (muſt or ſhall, a great choice and kindneſs truly) <hi>this is alſo appointed by God, whether at home or abroad, whether in the field or in the houſe, whether in the lower or upper rooms, whether at table</hi> (the round or long) <hi>or by the fire ſide,</hi> (or in the midſt of the fire) <hi>whether in the bed</hi> (the flock, feather, or doun-bed) <hi>or in a Chair,</hi> (the blew or the red.) 3. <hi>As to the manner of dying, or kind of death,</hi> mille modi Lethi, <hi>as the Poet ſaith; whether it ſhall be a ſudden or a lingring death,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:180513:13"/> (an Apoplexy or Conſumption,) <hi>whether it ſhall be a natural or a violent death,</hi> (by old age or by poyſon) <hi>whether in Peace or in War,</hi> Foraign or Domeſtick, <hi>(whether by ſickneſs, and by what ſickneſs</hi> (whether great or ſmall, by the biting of a Flea or a Viper, by a ſtab with a Stelletto or a ſtraw, by the ſhot of a Blunderbus or a Pop-gun; for ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the very time, manner, and place of every mans death are fatally determined, there is no more danger in the one, than in the other,) <hi>or by the hand of Juſtice; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by burning at the ſtake, hanging on the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, or loſing ones head on the Scaffold.</hi> Iſa. 22. 18. Jer. 11. 12. Jer. 34. 5. Joh. 12. 31. 32. Joh. 21. 19. Mat. 23. 34. 1 Pet. 4. 19. (And ſo from the firſt Chapter of <hi>Geneſis</hi> to the laſt of the <hi>Revelations.) All theſe circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, I ſay,</hi> (but ſhall never be able to prove) <hi>are appointed, determined, and limited by Gods unchangeable purpoſe.</hi> (Theſe comfortable Doctrines are calculated for <hi>New-gate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THE firſt ſix Quotations out of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles, are Predictions only of ſome certain mens death; as of <hi>Shebna,</hi> King <hi>Zedekiah,</hi> the men of <hi>Judah</hi> and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and of the bleſſed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:180513:13"/> 
               <hi>Jeſus,</hi> whoſe death upon all accounts is to be reſpected as a Caſe extraordinary; and therefore they argue nothing for a fatal Period, as I intimated before. And the laſt <hi>(viz.</hi> 1 Pet. 4. 19.) is as impertinent and ridiculous, as if I ſhould cite the firſt Chap. of St. <hi>John,</hi> or any other, to prove that there be as many Worlds, (as ſome with their Teleſcopes would perſwade us) as there are Stars in the Firmament. The words run thus, <hi>Wherefore let them that ſuffer according to the will of God, commit the keeping of their Souls to him in well-doing, as unto a faithful Creator.</hi> No man in his Wits would ever think, that this place could in the leaſt prove, or ſeem to favour a fatal Period; or, to uſe his own words, <hi>That God in his unchangeable purpoſe hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, and determin'd the time, the manner,</hi> (tho it be hanging on the Gallows for Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for Patricide; or loſing ones head on the Scaffold for Treaſon;) <hi>and place</hi> (Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burn, Tower-hill;) <hi>of mens death;</hi> unleſs it be becauſe there is one word in it, viz. <hi>Suffer.</hi> This was ever a fanatical Trick to amuſe and delude the Vulgar; for let them hear a Legion of Allegations from the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:180513:14"/> (tho not one of them to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, as here.) they inſtantly admire, and adore the man as an Angel or Meſſenger from Heaven; ſtyle him a Gifted, Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-learned, and powerful Preacher, that he hath all the Bible at his Fingers end, and had a Text for every word he thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd out of his wide Throat. Whereas others are for Reaſon, ancient Records, Councils, Fathers, and the like humane Learning. Thus having the credulous Multitude faſt by the Noſe, 'tis no diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult Province to inſtil into them the moſt erroneous, ſchiſmatical, and factious Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents, as the moſt perſpicuous Truths; well knowing that they want either Wit or Time to try and examine them. Read the ſeven preceding Verſes, and you will find, that the Apoſtle there only predicts, what great preſſures and afflictions the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Converts would be loaded with, for the ſake of their new (and therefore as their Enemies, both Jews and Gentiles thought falſe) Religion. That ſo by know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this before-hand, Perſecution might not unexpectedly ſurpriſe them, and cauſe them either to fluctuate or apoſtatize,</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:180513:14"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Beloved, think it not ſtrange concerning the fiery tryal</hi> (terrible fire of Perſecution) <hi>which is to try you: But rejoyce in as much as ye are partakers of Chriſts ſufferings; that when his glory ſhall be revealed, ye may be glad alſo with exceeding joy, If ye be reproached for the Name of Chriſt, happy are ye; for the ſpirit of glory and of God reſteth upon you: on their part he is evil ſpoken of, but on your part he is glorified. But let none of you</hi> (pray obſerve it, for this Caution is directly againſt a fatal Period, and intimates that the kind or manner of their death, was not abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely appointed; for they might ſuffer death for their wickedneſs, as well as for their Religion; or elſe the Precept or Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice (call it which you will) muſt needs be very ridiculous) <hi>ſuffer as a murtherer, or as a thief, or as an evil doer, or as a buſie-body in other mens matters. But if any ſuffer as a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, let him not be aſhamed; but let him glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie God on this behalf. For the time is come that judgment muſt begin at the houſe of God;</hi> (for the tryal of the righteous) <hi>and if it firſt begin at us,</hi> (the true Proſelytes of Chriſt) <hi>what ſhall be the end of them</hi> (the Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifiers of the holy Jeſus, and the obdurate
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:180513:15"/> Perſecuters of Chriſtianity) <hi>that obey not the Goſpel of God?</hi> (but utter exciſion.) <hi>And if the righteous ſcarcely be ſaved,</hi> (have afflictions in this life,) <hi>where ſhall the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly and ſinner appear?</hi> (how dreadful then is the expectation of the prophane?) <hi>Wherefore let them that ſuffer according to the will of God,</hi> (that ſuffer in the cauſe of their Saviour,) <hi>commit the keeping of their Souls to him in well-doing as unto a faithful Creator.</hi> (bear their preſſures patiently, and commit their lives to God, who will, if he ſees good, preſerve them; or elſe make their ſufferings a way and paſſage to Eternity.) This is enough to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate (tho we ſhall have other occaſions hereafter) to his knowing Editor, with the reſt of his Sticklers; or to any other that hath but common reaſon; how groſly Gods Word is abuſed and wreſted from its ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine and proper ſenſe, to prop and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronize his Heterodoxies and Mahometan phrenzies.</p>
            <p>TO affirm dogmatically, that decollati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſuſpenſion, <hi>felo de ſe,</hi> or any other mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable death that happen to men; yea, and all the curſed means thereto, as fraud,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:180513:15"/> rapine, treaſon, ſacriledge, murther, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are all abſolutely appointed by Gods im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable counſel and purpoſe; theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions (I ſay) of the Almighty, dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate much from his goodneſs, mercy, and truth; and are not only diametrically oppoſite to his very nature, who is Love in the abſtract, 1 Epiſt. St <hi>Joh.</hi> 4. 8. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and cannot be the Author of ſin; but to all the ſacred Monuments &amp; Records which evince, That the Period of every mans Life is mutable, and may be extended or ſhortned by Providence or Art, by God or Man. For,</p>
            <p>THE great God may (as all muſt yield, that will not deny his Attribute of Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potency, or make him a neceſſary Agent.) prolong or ſhorten the days of any man; and our Prayers, Repentance, the ſalubri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and purity of the Air and Water, our temperance and choice in eating and drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and the knowing and prudent Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian, may by Gods bleſſing extend our days: Whereas prophaneneſs, our immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate paſſions and deſires, the corrupted and impure Elements, our exceſs in any reſpect, expoſing our ſelves to any great
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:180513:16"/> and eminent perils, as the Sword or Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence; or an ignorant and confident Quack with his ſtrong and improper Medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, may ſhorten our days. And he that denies this, (as <hi>W. C.</hi> out of abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of humility, or rather ignorance doth) may as well contradict and deny not only his own reaſon, (reaſon did I ſay? that is a moſt ſcandalous and impious thing for a meek and mortified man, that is full of Raptures and Illuminations, to own;) but alſo his own experience, and the ſacred Hiſtory it ſelf. Firſt,</p>
            <p>'TIS evident from the Scriptures, That there is no fatal Period, but that our lives may be extended or ſhortned.</p>
            <p>OUR gracious Maker has promiſed long life to thoſe that fear him, and obſerve his Mandates. <hi>Deus his qui ipſum timent,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>fore promittit.</hi> Exod. 20. 12. Deut. 4. 40. 5. 16, 33. 8. 1. Pſal. 9. 16. Prov. 4. 10. Eph. 6. 2, 3. 1 Tim. 4. 8.</p>
            <p>AND God threatens the wicked, that for their impieties he will cut them off in the midſt of their Age, that they shall not live ſo long as otherwiſe they might. <hi>Lev.</hi> 26. 25. <hi>Deut.</hi> 5. 25, 26. 6. 15. 7. 10. 8. 19.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:180513:16"/> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55. 23. 104. 35. 109. 8. <hi>Prov.</hi> 10. 27.</p>
            <p>FROM the Examples of <hi>Er</hi> and <hi>Onan</hi> Gen. 38 7, 10. of <hi>Corah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram</hi> Numb. 16. 32, 33. of the <hi>Jews,</hi> Exo. 31. 14, 15; of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> Exod. 14. 28. of <hi>Abſolon</hi> 2 Sam. 18. 9; of <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira</hi> Acts 5. 5, 10. But were there a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Period, all theſe Promiſes and Menaces muſt needs be vain, falſe, and ridiculous; which to affirm or imagine would be no ſmall blaſphemy: And the ſad Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrophes of the forementioned, of <hi>Er</hi> and <hi>Onan,</hi> of <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira,</hi> &amp;c. were the reſults of his eternal and abſolute De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees, and not of his wrath and juſt Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. And that tho <hi>Corah</hi> and his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates did not die the common death of men, but the earth open'd her mouth, and ſwallowed them up; yet in <hi>(W. C</hi>'s Opinion, pag. 9.) they liv'd out all the days of their ſpecial and perſonal li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit; or all the days appointed as their portion in the land of the living. This methinks looks Legerdemain, than honeſt and ſound Theology.</p>
            <p>THERE are two places of holy Writ,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:180513:17"/> (amongſt ſeveral others, ſome whereof anon I ſhall have occaſion to nominate,) which may cauſe <hi>W. C.</hi> to ſtrike ſail, and yeeld to right and truth, if the ſimple En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comiums of the Vulgar, and of the factious Party, have not metamorphoz'd, and puft him up into a carnal ſtate (which he tells us is very dangerous, and in this we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve him;) of arrogancy and ſelf-adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>THE firſt is, <hi>Jer.</hi> 21. 8, 9. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, Behold I ſet before you the way of life, and the way of death. He that abideth in this City ſhall die by the ſword, and by the famine, and by the peſtilence; but he that goeth out, and falleth to the Caldeans that beſiege you, he ſhall live, and his life ſhall be to him for a prey.</hi> Which clearly demonſtrates, that the time, manner, and place of their death, were not limited and determined by any abſolute and unchangeable purpoſe or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of God; for 'twas in their own choice and power either to extend or ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten their days. If they would remain in the City, they ſhould die; if forſake it, they ſhould live.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:180513:17"/>
            <p> THE ſecond is the fifth Commandment, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. 12. which only hath a Promiſe annext to it: <hi>Honour thy father and mother,</hi> that is, thy civil Parents, (the King, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates;) thy Eccleſiaſtical Parents, (Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Paſtors;) as well as thy natural Parents, that brought thee into the world; <hi>that thy days may be long in the land. [That]</hi> here intimates not the final cauſe, but the event; (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as the Grammarians ſpeak) for this is not the end of our obedience, but an event and a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent to follow upon it: and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe is uſed as a motive to give honor to whom honor is due. To clear the truth of this, we muſt obſerve firſt, That all the Promiſes of God for temporal things, as for life, health, wealth, are conditional, not abſolute; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34. 12, 13, 14. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 10, 11. Mat. 6. 33. and ſhall ſo far be performed as may make for our good; and therefore in <hi>Deut.</hi> 5. 16. the Promiſe is thus limited and declar'd: <hi>Honour thy Father and thy Mother that thy days may be prolonged, and that it may go well with thee.</hi> So that the meaning is, (ſaith the moſt Reverend and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:180513:18"/> Learned Bp. of <hi>Gloceſter</hi> in his Exp.) that ſo long as it may go well with any man, his life ſhall be prolonged as no farther; but if his life prove to him a diſpleaſure and no benefit, it ſhall be taken away, and an eternal, which is far better, beſtowed on him. Thus it happen'd to <hi>Joſiah,</hi> 2 Kings 22. 20. <hi>Thou ſhalt be gathered into thy grave in peace, and thine eyes ſhall not ſee all the evil which I will bring on this place.</hi> Or ſecondly, That it may go well with thee, may carry this ſenſe, which St. <hi>Paul</hi> intimates, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 2. <hi>Honor and pray for Kings, that you may lead a quiet and peaceable life;</hi> for where this holy Order is broken and abroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, all peace and quietneſs (as our ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Diſſentions prov'd) is diſturb'd, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but blood, wounds, and confuſion follow. Or thirdly, This might ſhew Gods Ordinance: For the Almighty commonly gives a healthy and long life to crown our obedience even before the Sons of men, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37. 22. <hi>Jer.</hi> 17. 11. In this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular the diſobedient Son was to be cut off by the hand of the Magiſtrate, and was to be ſtoned, <hi>Deut.</hi> 21. 18. And <hi>Solomon</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:180513:18"/> tells us, <hi>Prov.</hi> 30. 17. <hi>The eye that mocketh at his Father, and deſpiſeth to obey his Mother, the Ravens of the valley ſhall pick it out, and the young Eagles ſhall eat it.</hi> By this we ſee that Gods Law was, that the undutiful Son should not be long-liv'd, should not live ſo long as the dutiful and obedient. Yea ſometimes God executes this ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance with his own hands, as upon <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah</hi> and his rebellious Aſſociates. The Story of the Kings, of all ancient and modern Records will aſſure us, That the Diſobedient, Thieves, Murtherers, Rebels, Traytors, were not long-liv'd; but periſhed often by the ſword and immature death.</p>
            <p>BUT our Lover of Humility, at the end of his Paraphraſe on this Commandment, flatly deny'd all this from the Pulpit, (and I muſt tell you in a Parentheſis, that I firſt animadverted on what <hi>W. C.</hi> preacht;) tho 'tis wiſely omitted by the Preſs; and affirm'd with no ſmall confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, (as <hi>G. S. W. G.</hi> and ſeveral others beſides my ſelf, will be depos'd;) viz. <hi>That we do ſee by Experience, That the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious and undutiful to Parents do live ſo</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:180513:19"/> 
               <hi>long as thoſe that are dutiful and obedient.</hi> A pure Catechiſt; For this, I preſume, is no <hi>infinitely Soul-concerning point</hi> (if I may ſpeak in his own Dialect) or precious Doctrine to inſpirit either men or chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to duty and obedience; but a grand Incentive for Villains to continue in their infernal plots and deſignes; or, when being detected, a <hi>Salvo</hi> for them; and is, if we may believe our own Experience, and the Word of truth it ſelf, a notorious falſity and deluſion, and clearly evacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates Gods promiſes. For Myriads, we know, of Rebels and Murtherers, in the moſt flouriſhing part of their lives, have been cut off by the ſword of Juſtice: But <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 5. <hi>Bleſſed are the meek; for they ſhall inherit the earth.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (Dr. <hi>Ham.)</hi> very often hath a peculiar Critical ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Goſpels, and refers to the Land of <hi>Judaea,</hi> and here by being promiſed to the meek and obedient, looks diſtinctly on the fifth Commandment, &amp; in it on the Land, <hi>which the Lord thy God giveth thee,</hi> i. e. a fruitful proſperous being here on earth, <hi>viz.</hi> long life and tranquillity;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:180513:19"/> which is here ſaid to belong by promiſe of God peculiarly to the meek. But when the exerciſes of this virtue of meekneſs and obedience in ſome ſingular conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures of time brings loſſes, or death up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them; they ſhall richly be rewarded in another world, and be made amends abundantly there for all that the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of this virtue hath brought on them.</p>
            <p>BUT it may be ſaid, (and that truly too, for ought I know;) that <hi>W. C.</hi> had not this <hi>(viz.</hi> That we do ſee by Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, <hi>&amp;c.)</hi> in his Notes. But this will not excuſe him; for ſhould I extol and preach up the Doctrine and Diſcipline of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> (as in Duty and Conſcience I ought,) and my Notes ſhould be very ſound and orthodox; yet if I ſhould tell my Auditors <hi>ex tempore,</hi> or without my Notes, That the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of Tranſubſtantiation, of Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, Invocation of Saints, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to Gods word; I know I ought and ſhould be queſtioned for it, and my Notes would not keep me in my Parſonage
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:180513:20"/> without an open Recantation, ſeeing there are honeſt Witneſſes enough to prove it.</p>
            <p>BUT to do <hi>W. C.</hi> all the right imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, I ſhall tranſcribe <hi>verbatim</hi> his new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>model'd Anſwers to two Texts of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which he thought might contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict (as indeed they doe) his former Aſſertions.</p>
            <p>FIRST <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7. 17. <hi>Be not overmuch wicked, neither be thou fooliſh, why ſhouldeſt thou die before thy time?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>ANSW. (pag. 8.) <hi>He that dies before his time, dyes not before the time which God hath determined; an unſeaſonable death to man, doth not prevent Gods ſeaſon: To clear which, we must diſtinguiſh about death, which is Two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold. Firſt, Natural; Secondly, Violent. A man that dies a violent death, is ſaid to dye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his time which he might have reached un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to by the courſe of nature; Sin cuts him off, before God cuts him off: But then God cuts him off for ſin. Thus many dye before their time; and except in this ſenſe, no man dies before his time.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:180513:20"/>
            <p> TRULY Sir, in this ſenſe (without aping you, &amp; ſtraining for Rimes and Quibles,) 'tis perfect nonſenſe; for how can a man that dies a Violent death, be properly ſaid in any ſenſe to dye before his time? when, according to your own words, <hi>(pag.</hi> 11.) God in his unchangeable pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe hath appointed, and determined the very moment, manner, and place of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mans death; whether Natural or Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent, whether by burning at the Stake, or hanging on the Gallows. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, we cannot truly affirm of many ſincere, pious, and virtuous men, that were remov'd hence by a Violent death; <hi>Jeremy</hi> was ſtoned, <hi>Ezekiel</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> cut aſunder, <hi>Eleazar,</hi> at the age of fourſcore years, cudgel'd to death, none of the eaſieſt doubtleſs; moſt of the Prophets and Apoſtles perſecuted and ſlain, St. <hi>Peter</hi> endur'd crucifixion with his head downward, according to his own requeſt, and St. <hi>Paul</hi> decollation, in one day at <hi>Rome,</hi> as <hi>Euſebius</hi> tells us; ſome burnt, others devoured by wild Beaſts, or the like deaths, as St. <hi>Polycar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus,</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:180513:21"/> 
               <hi>Ignatius,</hi> St. <hi>Laurence, Cyprian,</hi> and Myriads which ſuffer'd under <hi>Nero, Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jan, Antonius, Severus, Maximinus,</hi> and <hi>Diocleſian</hi> who everted Churches, and made the ſacred Bibles become fuel to devouring flames; We dare not, I ſay, judge, That Sin did cut thoſe glorious Saints off, (becauſe they ſuffer'd Violent deaths,) before God did cut them off; and that then God did cut them off for ſin: for this were a ſigne of Gods ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, wrath, and fury. But rather that God did cut them off, before Sin did cut them off; either for the advancement of his honor and glory, the good of the Church, (for <hi>ſanguis Martyrum eſt ſemen Eccleſiae;)</hi> or to free them from fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture miſeries and calamities, which otherwiſe might befal them. So <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 57. 1. <hi>The righteous is taken away from the evil to come.</hi> All which are infallible To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of Gods infinite mercy and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſe love.</p>
            <p>SECONDLY, <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55. 2. <hi>That bloody and deceitful men, ſhall not live out half their days.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:180513:21"/>
            <p> ANSW. (pag. 9.) <hi>For anſwer to this you muſt know (Beloved) that there is a general and ſpecial, or perſonal limit of man's Life.</hi> 1. <hi>The general Limit is Seventy or Eighty years.</hi> Pſal. 90. <hi>The few exceptions which ſome have made by exceeding this limit, weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens not this general Rule.</hi> 2. <hi>There is a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular limit upon every perſon; the limit of one may be Forty years, when another is tied to Thirty, a third to Twenty, a fourth to Five, and a fifth perhaps may be tied to Four years; theſe are ſpecial Limits upon ſpecial men. Now when the Pſalmiſt ſaith,</hi> That a bloody and deceitful man ſhall not live out half his days; <hi>the meaning</hi> (the ſubverting) <hi>of it is, that he ſhall not live out half the days of mans general limit: As ſuppoſe a bloody man be cut off at Thirty, he hath not lived out half Seventy or Eighty years, which are the common terms of Life preſcribed unto Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, beyond which they cannot paſs; but this man lives out all the days of his ſpecial and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal limit, or all his days which are appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as his portion in the Land of the living. Thus the bloodieſt man that is, let him dye</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:180513:22"/> 
               <hi>when he will, dyes in the particular ſeaſon ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed unto him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A prolix, frivolous, and childiſh An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, tho perhaps he may think it very Scholaſtick; the ſubſtance whereof in ſhort is this: <hi>David</hi> (Beloved) dreams, That bloody men ſhall not live out half their days; but I (your Oracle) aſſure you, That the bloodieſt man that is, lives out all the days of his ſpecial and perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal limit; or all his days which are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed as his portion in the Land of the living. If this is ſound and Authentique, (profound Sir) What difference then (in reſpect of a long Life or a ſhort,) is there between the blood-thirſty and merciful, the fraudulent and juſt? For a precious Saint can but live out all the days of his ſpecial and perſonal limit, or all the days which are appointed as his portion in the Land of the Living; and ſo (in your judgment) doth every notorious and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Rogue. But ſuppoſe a Felon or Murtherer is executed at three or four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:180513:22"/> years (as hath often happen'd,) then, according to your own account, his days cannot be ſaid to be ſhortned in any reſpect; for he hath liv'd out all the days both of his general and ſpecial limit. If our popular Holderforth is not paſt ſhame and all goodneſs, he may do well (if the <hi>Parcae</hi> will permit,) to recal his Pamphlets, which with a great deal of oſtentation he has ſcatter'd amongſt the Vulgar, and reſign them to <hi>Vulcan,</hi> or my Lords-houſe for neceſſary uſes; for he that hath but half an eye, may without an Optick-glaſs ſee, how notoriouſly the ſacred Writ is contradicted, tortur'd, and ſcandaliz'd by his petty Diſtinctions.</p>
            <p>THE Almighty, we concede, may permit (but not abſolutely and peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torily determine and appoint,) the fall either of this man or that; yea he may permit (for ends beſt known to himſelf,) the meek, obedient, and virtuous to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer by or with the prophane: As we have known Royal Innocency to be ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign'd as the vileſt Criminal, and he that was inferior to God only, to be mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther'd,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:180513:23"/> like the holy Jeſus, by the fury and out-cry of the unſtable Multitude, the very Scum and Rabble. Yet this He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roick and ever bleſſed Martyr never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pin'd, and exclaim'd againſt Gods me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods and dealings as unjuſt or unequal; but gave us the reaſon of all our ſad diſaſters and heavy preſſures. Our Sins (ſaith he in his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) being ripe, there was no preventing of Gods juſtice from reaping that glory in our calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which we rob'd him of in our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity. For puniſhments are but the reſults of ſins; and therefore whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Malignity lies in the effect becomes entirely chargeable upon the Cauſe, and we are to look upon our Vice not only as our greateſt but our only unhappineſs. Our numerous and gygantick Provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions did call for judgments, and that the expiring of the <hi>Breath of our Noſtrils,</hi> was a great one, the whole Nation ſoon felt, lay gaſping, ready to bid adieu to all ſublunary comforts. For God in his ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice to Us ſhorten'd his days, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd for a time Tyrants on his Throne,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:180513:23"/> to become Sirens and Crocodiles to faſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and trapan, and Lictors to ſcurge us; but in his mercy to Him, remov'd him hence, from the evil and miſeries approaching; and crown'd him firſt with Martyrdom, and then with glory. <hi>Una eadem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> manus vulnus opemque.</hi> The rod of our Maker when it falls upon the virtuous, being, like that of an indulgent Parent upon his only Child, the ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt argument of love and affection. He intends the greateſt pity, when to the Spectators that are ignorant of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, he ſeems moſt cruel and inexora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; and when he ſeems to patronize and favour the Stratagems of the vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, 'tis only that Their fall and His glory might be the greater; and that they might in the height of their arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancie and preſumption, like lofty <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh</hi> and his army, eternally ſink and periſh. But many inconſiderate men, we know, are much ſtartled, and ſecretly murmur;</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:180513:24"/> Qui cumres hominum tantac aligine volvi Aſpicerent, laetoſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> diu florere nocentes Vexari<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> pios.</q>
            <p>So holy <hi>David</hi> had a zealous indignation againſt the ſucceſſes of the wicked, and repin'd to ſee them thrive in wealth and grandeur; but when he had recourſe to Gods Sanctuary, and enter'd into a ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous conſideration of his counſels and providence, he ſoon perceiv'd the Scene to be alter'd, and that their Proſperity was no more but like that of a dream whilſt it laſts 'tis imaginary not real. <hi>Fret not thy ſelf then becauſe of evil doers, neither be thou envious againſt the workers of iniquity. For they ſhall ſoon be cut down like the graſs, and wither as the green herb. But thoſe that wait upon the Lord, thoſe ſhall inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit the earth.</hi> Pſal. 37. 1, 2, 9. The gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral common end of the wicked is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timely exciſion, ſignal puniſhments even in this Life; mind the ſad Exits of the <hi>Sodomites,</hi> of <hi>Herod, Judas, Simon Magus, Arius, Julian</hi> the Apoſtate; of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirators
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:180513:24"/> and Murtherers of our late dread Soveraign, <hi>Doriſlaus</hi> and <hi>Aſcham</hi> ſtab'd, <hi>Hoyle</hi> hang'd himſelf, <hi>Norton,</hi> being diſquieted in mind, dyed raving mad; <hi>Harriſon, Scot, Carew, Jones<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Scroop, Axtel,</hi> precious <hi>Hugh Peters</hi> hang'd and quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd: But we ſhall not aſcribe their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorable and immature deaths as happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning unto them from the eternal Decrees, or from Gods unchangeable purpoſe; but from their own demerits, and Gods juſt judgments. Whereas the Lot of the pious and obedient is length of days, and proſperity in this World; but if that fail, as God in his infinite wiſdom ſometimes ſees good tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it ſhould, an abundant compenſation of bliſs in the Life to come ſhall be moſt certain. <hi>He that loſeth his life for my ſake</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>ſhall find it.</hi> Mat. 10. 39. The loſs of a ſhort temporary Life ſhall be rewarded with an eternal.</p>
            <p>THERE is one place (upon which <hi>W. C.</hi> wholy depends that at the firſt aſpect may ſeem to favour a fatal Period; <hi>Job.</hi> 14. 5. <hi>His days are determined, the number</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:180513:25"/> 
               <hi>of his months are with thee, thou haſt appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his bounds which he cannot paſs.</hi> Upon which words two learned Criticks com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments thus: <hi>Significat hic apud Deum eſſe certiſſimam praeſcientiam dierum &amp; menſium quibus homo victurus ſit, ex qua tamen non ſequitur neceſſitas rei (nam res eſt contingens) ſed tantum neceſſitas conſequentiae.</hi> The days and years of mans life, in reſpect of Gods preſcience are determined and moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain; but from hence it doth not follow that the thing it ſelf, mans time is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily determined, (for 'tis contingent and vareable,) but only the neceſſity of the conſequence; becauſe God, whoſe eyes cannot be deceiv'd, ſees all things <hi>uno intuitu,</hi> that our days and months will be thus long, or thus ſhort.</p>
            <p>SO the Metaph. tell us: <hi>Quae Deus praeſcit non poſſunt non evenire, &amp; ſic habent neceſſitatem fiendi. Id<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> propter infallibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem praeſcientiae divinae. Res enim ſic di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuntur neceſſariae non niſi per connexionem ad aliud, hoc eſt, praeſcientiam divinam. Loquen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do autem de rebus in ſe ſpectatis, quae praeſciun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, remota connexione ad praeſcientiam divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam,</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:180513:25"/> 
               <hi>non omnes res ſunt neceſſariae, quae ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſit as eſt conſequentis. Sunt enim multa in mundo caſualia, fortuita, libera, quae omnia in ſe ſpectata non neceſsaria ſed contingentia ſunt. Fiunt proculdubio cuncta, ait</hi> Boet. <hi>quae futur a Deus praenoſcit; ſed eorum quaedam proficiſcuntur de libero; quae quamvis eveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant, tamen propriam naturam non amittunt, ſed priuſquam fierent etiam non evenire po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuiſsent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND ſays the other; <hi>Cauſae naturales &amp; morales ſuos habent effectus in vita homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis conſervanda. Deus igitur illas in conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuendo termino vitae, ut omniſcius reſpexit, ita tamen ut eas, uhi velit inhibere poſsit.</hi> Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and moral Cauſes, as wholſom food, air, water, continency, temperance <hi>&amp;c.</hi> have their effects and operations in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving mans Life; and God in termina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and ſetting Boundaries to mans Life, as he is Omniſcient and foreſees all things, hath an eye and reſpect to theſe; yet ſo that he can put a Stop to thoſe natural and moral Cauſes, can in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibit them, as in his infinite wiſdom he ſees fit. As for Example, God ſees that
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:180513:26"/> ſuch a man living and doing thus and thus, will, according to the ordinary courſe of nature, certainly live thus long, ſuppoſe fifty, ſixty, ſeventy years; yet God may cauſe that this man that might live thus long, ſhall dye much ſooner, as at twenty or thirty. So God in his mercy may ſhorten the days of many righteous men, take them away from the evil to come; or in his juſtice cut off the wicked, that according to the ſtrength of nature, and the ſet bounds thereof, might have liv'd much longer. Yea <hi>Job</hi> himſelf is againſt a fatal Period, and therefore we cannot imagine if he intended it in the 14 Chap. he would have contradicted both himſelf and it in the 21 Chap. 19, 20, 21. ver. God layeth up his iniquity for his children, he rewardeth him, and he ſhall know it. His eyes ſhall ſee his deſtruction, and he ſhall drink of the wrath of the Almighty. For what pleaſure hath he in his houſe after him, <hi>when the number of his months are cut off in the midſt. W. C.</hi> being now forc'd from his ſtrong Hold, which he thought
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:180513:26"/> invincible;; 'twill be his wiſeſt way to addreſs himſelf to the Alchoran, where he may find more kindneſs, and need not fear a ſecond repulſe.</p>
            <p>NEITHER may mens lives be ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten'd only, but alſo extended; whereof we have a pregnant example in the 2 Kings 20. beg. For God plainly ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> that he ſhould dye of that very diſtemper he then labour'd un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; for he was come to the ſet Bounds, beyond which he could not paſs, except Omnipotency be pleaſed to remove them farther. So ver. 1. <hi>Hezekiah</hi> was ſick unto death, and the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> came, and ſaid to him. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, Set thy houſe in order, for thou ſhalt dye, and not live.</hi> Yet the immutable Creator that decrees mutability, (as the learned Dr. <hi>Jackſon</hi> words it,) and whoſe promiſes and menaces are not abſolute but condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional; hearing his Prayers, and ſeeing his tears, remov'd the Boundary, reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd him with a lump of figs, (to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate the uſe and neceſſity of means,) and added to his Life fifteen years. And
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:180513:27"/> therefore <hi>W. C</hi>'s Gloſs is very prodigious and Enthuſiaſtick, (pag. 8.) <hi>The fifteen years added to</hi> Hezekiah<hi>'s Life, were added to</hi> Hezekiah<hi>'s date, not to Gods.</hi> Hezekiah <hi>looked upon himſelf as a dead man, that he ſhould dye of that very ſickneſs,</hi> (and good reaſon, ſeeing God told him ſo;) <hi>and ſo in all likelihood did his beſt Phyſicia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, for he was ſick of the Plague; but both he and they were deceiv'd: for God in his unchangeable pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, had appointed fifteen years more to</hi> He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah<hi>'s Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>STRANGE indeed: For we find in the Chapter no ſuch learned Cheats and Pick-pockets, (as all Phyſitians are, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing a fatal Period;) nor the leaſt ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of ſuch an interpretation: for God himſelf ſaid by the mouth of his Prophet, <hi>I have heard thy Prayer, and I will add unto thy days fifteen years, and I will deliver thee and this City</hi> &amp;c. And as a ſign that God himſelf would effect this, and did not prevaricate; a Miracle is wrought, he brought the ſhadow (the Sun) ten de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees backward by which it had gon down in the dial of <hi>Ahaz.</hi> But were the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:180513:27"/> former Paraphraſe true, God himſelf made—, and the Prophet told a Lie, and was deceiv'd, as well as <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah</hi> and his Phyſicians; and the words ſhould not run, The Lord will, or did really add to <hi>Hezekiah</hi>'s days fifteen years; but <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> the Prophet, the Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, with all the Nobles and Courtiers, not well underſtanding this infinitely Soul-concerning Point, <hi>viz.</hi> a Fatal Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod; were ſo ſimple and credulous as to believe that God had miraculouſly exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Hezekiah</hi>'s Life: (and who can think otherwiſe, that reads and believes this ſacred Hiſtory?) Whereas God had ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely decreed from eternity, or in his unchangeable purpoſe appointed, (there is not the leaſt difference in the Phraſes,) that <hi>Hezekiah</hi> ſhould live fifteen years longer; which being not expir'd, 'twas impoſſible for the Plague, or for God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to put an end to his days. A feeble and impotent God that can neither ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend nor ſhorten the Lives of his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. 'Tis wonderful to ſee, that one petty Diſtinction (in Mans date, but
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:180513:28"/> not in Gods,) ſhould be of ſuch mighty force as to enervate ſo many plain Texts of Scripture, as have been, and may be produc'd for the prolonging and ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of mans Life; and to make them ſpeak quite contrary, even to become like a Noſe of Wax, to turn either to this ſide or that, to prove truth to be falſhood, and falſhood truth. Should I be trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with ſuch an airy and Atheiſtical Whimſie, as to affirm with ſome of the ancient Peripateticks and Ethnicks, That the World is eternal; (tho <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf doubted <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.) And againſt it is objected <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 1. <hi>In the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning God created the heaven and the earth,</hi> Ergo <hi>Mundus non fuit ab aeterno.</hi> I ſhall moſt humbly crave <hi>W. C</hi>'s leave, borrow his almighty diſtinction, and anſwer very magiſterially, as he did to the Lords ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Hezekiah</hi>'s days fifteen years. 'Tis true, in mans date, <hi>viz.</hi> in the date and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of <hi>Moſes, Aaron,</hi> and their Bigots, the World had a beginning; but in Gods date 'twas eternal: for God in his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable purpoſe had appointed it
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:180513:28"/> from Eternity, Such ſtuff as this will paſs for ſuperfine Doctrine; for power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Preaching and ſublime Raptures, with thoſe that have their Inſtructers of the <hi>Geneva</hi> ſtamp in as great admiration be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of advantage, <hi>Jude</hi> 16. as the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Papiſts have their Monks and Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, or even as his Holineſs the Pope himſelf.</p>
            <p>THE learned and judicious <hi>Beverovi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius,</hi> before he could think that his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion could find any conſiderable enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment among men, thought it fit to be ſtated by the knowing men of his Age; <hi>viz.</hi> Whether there were a fatal end of every man's life, beyond which it were not in the power and compaſs of art, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety, or good managery to extend it; and as little in the power of any Diſeaſe or Intemperance, or even the Famine, Plague, or Sword to ſhorten it? Should the ſame Queſtion be again ſtarted, no conſidering men, I preſume, would hold the affirmative. For we daily ſee the ſad effects and reſults of intemperance and inordinate living; we have often
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:180513:29"/> ſeen, felt, or heard of the impartial and mighty power of the Sword and Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence; how Myriads have been cut off, that according to the ſtrength and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary courſe of nature, and Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Providence, might have liv'd much longer. And therefore we are not ſo ſtupid and zealouſly Lunatick, as not to fear the frequent Afterclaps (Feavers, Dropſies, Surfeits,) of high and conſtant debaucheries, or the Fury of inſulting Enemies, and infectious Diſeaſes. Our moſt mortifyed and ſtouteſt Combatants for fatal and neceſſary events, will ſuffer their actions to contradict their Faith, (tho <hi>Proteſtatio contra factum non valet;)</hi> and be thought timorous and ignorant Creatures, even quake and fly, to ſave their Lives, from any imminent danger; which, ſuppoſing their firm belief and confidence of a fatal Period, is a piece of notorious Folly. For if neither intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, the Sword, or Plague, can ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten our days one minute; I would fain know, in reſpect of our Health and Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, why we ſhould dread them, or avert
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:180513:29"/> from either; why <hi>Bacchus</hi> and <hi>Venus,</hi> dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly carouzing and obſcene Embraces are reſpected, yea are known and profeſt Foes to Longaevity; why we may not reſt as ſecurely in a Peſt-houſe, as on a bed of Roſes, as ſafe before a Cannons mouth, as in our Cloſets? And ſo our Saviours Advice (who minds the wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of our Bodies as well as of our Souls,) muſt needs be vain and ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. 23. <hi>When they perſecute you in this City, flee into another.</hi> For no Aſylum, or City of Refuge (granting a fatal Peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od) can ſave us, or extend our days the leaſt point of time. And ſo this precept or prudent Counſel of Chriſt to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, (viz. <hi>To flee from Perſecution,)</hi> is as <hi>thwarting</hi> to <hi>W. C.</hi>'s. Doctrine, as he tells us <hi>(pag.</hi> 18.) that of <hi>Martha</hi>'s to him was; If thou hadſt been here my Brother had not dyed. Sir 'tis my hearty requeſt that you would not be paſſionate, and queſtion the Holy Jeſus, as you ſeem to do poor ſilly St. <hi>Martha,</hi> for her confiding in our Saviours power, and love to her Brother; That if he had been there,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:180513:30"/> 
               <hi>Lazarus</hi> had not dyed; ſaying, Is not this advice a thwarting of my Doctrine? Can fleeing from Perſecution free us from Death, or extend our days one minute? ſeeing <hi>all the particular circumſtance, rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to it</hi> (viz. the time, manner, and place) <hi>are unchangeably appointed by Gods inſupera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Power.</hi> This Counſel, 'tis confeſt, of the Theanthropos, is a thwarting to your fatal and dogmatical Aſſertions; and ſo is <hi>Davids</hi> addreſs to the Lord, Pſal. 102. 24. <hi>O my God, take me not away in the midſt of my days.</hi> Here is thwart upon thwart to try your <hi>Job-</hi>like Patience, and preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Wit, in forging ſome new Diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and riming Evaſions, ſeeing the Old ones are detected, and already ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhier'd.</p>
            <p>BUT farther, Were this Stoical Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (fit indeed for ſanguinary Deſigns, to animate <hi>Turks</hi> and ambitious Rebels;) moſt clear and demonſtrative; the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians then may burn their Books, <hi>Galen</hi> and <hi>Hypocrates;</hi> and the Apothecaries and Surgeons may pull down their Shops, and hang themſelves (if they are aſham'd
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:180513:30"/> to beg,) for want of bread, or elſe the Magiſtrates may do it for them, as being the vileſt cheats in Nature; but howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever let me adviſe them that for pity ſake, that they would no longer vex and torment their ſimple Patients with Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks and Scarifyings, nor ſaw off Legs and Arms tho gangreen'd: the very mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, manner, and place of their Death are fixt and unalterable; no Art imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, no fervent Prayers, no gracious Providence can do them the leaſt good. If the Eternal Decree is, that this Patient ſhall dye of this gangrene, 'tis fruſtrane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, yea cruelty to cut off the mortifyed member; but if the Decree is, that he ſhall live longer, and dye of ſome other Diſtemper; let the Part be never ſo much putrifyed, he ſhall certainly (tho you apply not the leaſt remedy,) live out all the days determined, or (as <hi>W. C.</hi> moſt profoundly words it,) <hi>all the days of his ſpecial and perſonal limit.</hi> What a ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous and ſilly thing 'tis, (ſuppoſing a fatal Period) for pregnant Females ſo highly to concern themſelves for fear of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:180513:31"/> abortion, to be ſo ſollicitous and inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive after a knowing Mid-wife, when old gooddy Tittle-tattle can perform the Office as well; and, when being deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd, to undergo ſuch cruel thirſts, and to take ſuch care and pains about the New born Infant? If the Decree is, that both the Mother and the Child ſhall live, a good Midwife or a bad, or none at all, quarts and pottles of ſtrong liquor, or clear Poſſets, Fiſh or Fleſh, they cannot dye; but if the Decree is, that one or both ſhall Dye, all the charges and care imaginable will be ineffectual. And therefore 'tis no ſmall madneſs to caſt away our Mony, and to be concern'd (as ſome ſoft-natur'd Goſſips are,) about this Nicety or that; for <hi>Praedeſt. ad finem, praedeſt. quoque ad media,</hi> if God has ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Life, he has likewiſe unavoidably, or in his unchangeable purpoſe ordain'd and appointed the means, or elſe he will preſerve it without them; but if Death is in the Pot, there is no avoiding of the Broth. This <hi>W. C.</hi> (if he underſtands his own Principles, which is much to be
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:180513:31"/> doubted;) and all the Irreſpective Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probatarians hold, and endeavour to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie; which takes away the liberty of mans will, and makes him inferior to Brutes, that by natural inſtinct chooſe what may conduce to the preſervation both of themſelves and their ſpecies, and avoid whatſoever is noxious and injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to them; whereas poor man is as ſenſeleſs, and incapacitated to do him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf either good or hurt, as a Stock or a Stone. For if the Decree is Life, it ſhall be life, do what we will; if Death, do what we can, Death. How abſurd and contrary to reaſon, experience, and to Gods frequent and ſerious Proteſtations and Invitations this is, the meaneſt ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity may eaſily judge?</p>
            <p>SHOULD a man in a ſudden and violent Diſtemper, a Surfeit, Pleuriſy, Apoplexy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> deſpiſe and deride the known and u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual Remedies, (as many of this Perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion have done; tho the moſt knowing of them will not truſt and depend upon this fatal <hi>Faith,</hi> but in their Sickneſs are as willing to ſend for a judicious Phyſitian
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:180513:32"/> as any;) and tell his mourning Friends and Relations, that he will not ſo much ſuſpect God as to try the skill of man, or be ſo imprudent as to fee a Fool or a Cheat: for the time, manner, and place of his Death are unchangeably appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Gods inſuperable Power. And therefore why do you talk of the uſe of Means? when the ſtrongeſt Poyſon can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſhorten my days; nor the richeſt Cordials, or God himſelf extend them one moment beyond my ſpecial and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal limit, beyond the time appointed as my Portion in the land of the living. And this I know to be true, for the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphical Preacher that taught and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed me in this <hi>ſecret and hidden point;</hi> (for Gods revealed word is againſt it,) is as infallible in the Pulpit, as the Pope is in Cathedra, and when there can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicate all obſcure doubts and hard Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, as eaſily as crack a nut with a ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. I ſhall for brevity ſake dilate only upon one, (tho I have been credibly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd of many others, <hi>viz.</hi> How many Millions that were at Church one Lords
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:180513:32"/> day, yet were in Hell the next; And that Hell is <hi>Spatium infinitum in loco fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to;</hi> infernally wiſe truly.) The next Sabbath day after he had inform'd us of the certainty of a fatal Period; from the ſame infallible Chair in <hi>O. C.</hi> Church, for the ſatisfaction of a zealous and ſcrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Brother, he inform'd us likewiſe of what ſubſtance our immortal Souls were made, viz. <hi>That the Souls of men are made of the very ſame Subſtance that the Angels are.</hi> Had our Angelical Praedicator aſſerted, That the Souls of men are made of the ſame Subſtance that the Man in the Moon is; his credulous and all-ear'd Creatures might have believ'd him; tho others might have thought him either Luna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, or troubled with a Vertigo, or elſe a little crackt in the Pericranion. And indeed the truth of the one, is no more apparent than that of the other; for the beſt Metaphyſicians affirm, That the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and Souls of men are of a divers ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and ſo doubtleſs of a divers ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. <hi>Nam eſſentia animae ex naturà ſuà eſt incompleta &amp; partialis, &amp; implicat natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralem</hi>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:180513:33"/> 
               <hi>propenſionem ad materiam. At verò tale quid eſsentiae Angelicae non convenit, quae eſt totalis &amp; completa: Id ergo indicium ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtum eſt diverſitatis ſpecificae.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall not make this an Article of my Creed, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Souls of men are made of the very ſame Subſtance that the Angels are; before I am aſcertain'd by this grand Philoſopher, who forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his Humility talks as if he had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menced Doctor with the Angels in Heaven; <hi>viz.</hi> That there is not the leaſt difference between Spiritual and immate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Subſtances, tho there is between groſs and corporeal. But to digreſs no farther; Should there, I ſay, be ſuch a mad Zealot for a fixt and inevitable Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod, that would try the truth of it by a plain hazard of his Life, <hi>felo de ſe,</hi> or the violation of the ſixth Commandment, <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill,</hi> eſpecially thy ſelf, by refuſing lawful and neceſſary means or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain'd by God himſelf, will be none of his ſmalleſt Crimes at the great and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Audit.</p>
            <p>SHOULD we ſee one in an extaſie, in a furious rage or diſcontent, drink Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:180513:33"/> Stab, Hang, or caſt himſelf from a Precipice; would we peremptorily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, (like <hi>W. C.)</hi> that this was the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry moment, this the very kind and place of Death, where this deſperate and wretched Miſcreant ſhould be hurried off the Stage of this World by a fatal and abſolute Decree? The Lord forbid that we ſhould harbor ſuch cruel thoughts of him that made and form'd us; that hath proclaim'd himſelf, and we dare believe him, to be merciful; that he is no <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and willeth not the death of a Sinner, but rather that he ſhould turn and live. And can we then be ſo prophane and ſottiſh, as to aver, even in Print, that this mad Creature, and Legions beſides that came to fearful and deplorable ends, by Melancholy, Deſpair, the Temptations of Satan, by Venery, Debauchery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were inevitably de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed by God, or in his immutable pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe determined and appointed to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come their own Executioners?</p>
            <p>BUT <hi>W. C.</hi> to make his ſordid matter
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:180513:34"/> as clear as the Sun in its Meridian, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>informs us; <hi>(pag.</hi> 16.) <hi>That there are Two</hi> (he might ſay as truly, ten hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand) <hi>ſorts of Divine appointments, What ſhould be. What ſhall be. What ſhould be: He hath ſhewed thee, O man, what is right; and what doth the Lord require of thee, but to do juſtly, to love Mercy, and to walk Humbly with thy God. God hath appointed that men ſhould be ſober, temperate, true, honeſt, juſt and ſquare in their dealings; God hath appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that men ſhould read, hear, pray, repent, believe, be convicted, and live holily. Theſe appointments of the Divine Majeſty, are dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſappointed and violated by wicked and ungodly men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>HERE (and in ſeveral other places, which would be too tedious to tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe,) our Oracle contradicts himſelf; for he would have all Gods Decrees and Appointments to be peremptory and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute, impoſſible to be diſappointed. So but three lines before the Miſterious Diſtinction, he tells us; <hi>Human appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments come to nothing, when God is againſt them, but Divine appointments ſhall stand,</hi>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:180513:34"/> that is cannot be diſappointed, And tho he ſtiles <hi>What ſhould be</hi> a Divine appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as well as <hi>What ſhall be;</hi> yet pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently forgetting himſelf, he rightly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms us, (tho directly contrary to his former Poſitions,) That thoſe Divine ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointments of <hi>What ſhould be, are daily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointed and violated by wicked and ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men.</hi> And by this moſt ridiculous Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction, he makes God to decree con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions; that altho God in his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable purpoſe hath appointed that All men ſhould be Holy, do Juſtly, and by conſequence be ſaved; yet the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality (as the event proves,) <hi>ſhould, or ſhall (utrum horum mavis)</hi> be unholy, yea neceſſarily damn'd. Which directs me to ſpeak ſomething concerning the Future State of the Soul.</p>
            <p>THE great Potentate of the Univerſe, 'tis true, may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, <note place="margin">The Future State of the Soul.</note> but not <hi>decree to permit,</hi> (as we were once told by <hi>W. C</hi>'s. learned Champion:) or in his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable purpoſe abſolutely determine and appoint either this Sin, or that Evil: for
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:180513:35"/> then the Puniſher of Sin muſt needs be the Author of it, and poor man muſt ſuffer for that which 'twas impoſſible for him to avoid: and the Almighty, we know, is not oblig'd by a Miracle always to hinder men from miſery and perdition. For he has made us ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Creatutes, and gives us ſtrength and grace, if we will but uſe and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove it, to follow that which is good and laudable, and to eſchew the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; to live well and contented, tho under the heavieſt preſſures, in this World, and after death, by the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of the holy Jeſus, who hath tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph't over both Hell and the Grave, to aſcend the Heavens, and to be crown'd with glory and immortality.</p>
            <p>AND God, we willingly grant, is immutable, <hi>James</hi> 1. 17. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 17. but then we muſt know and remember, that this Immutability does not limit or confine God, or determine, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain, or force mens wills and actions; or certainly and neceſſarily appoint or
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:180513:35"/> infer either this man's bliſs, or that man's miſery.</p>
            <q>IMMUTABILITAS divinae volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis non eſt intelligenda poſſitivê, hoc eſt quaſi Deus non poſſit velle mutatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem vel varietatem rerum: Nec in ſenſu diviſo, hoc eſt, antequam quaſi uni oppoſitorum conjuncta eſt. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tequam enim Deus decernit punire aliquem hominem, poterat uti<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> non decernere. Et haec eſt ipſa radix li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertatis. Unde ſi aliquod Agens dice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur immutabile in ſenſu diviſo, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vera non eſſet liberum, quia libertas conſiſtit in hoc, ut poſſit quis diviſivè velle &amp; non velle idem. Sed immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabilitas voluntatis divinae intelligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da eſt in ſenſu compoſito, hoc eſt, Si Deus actuali volitione ſe ad aliquam rem determinaverit, eſt conſtans &amp; tenax propoſiti. Et haec eſt immuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitas voluntatis, quae nihil pugnat cum ejuſdem libertate.</q>
            <p>AND the ſupreme Monarch of the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:180513:36"/> whole World, 'tis confeſt on all ſides, ſees all things, all accidental and caſual events; but <hi>Praeſcientia nil ponit,</hi> this Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg doth not neceſſitate or compel men either to this or that, to this Virtue or that Vice, to Life or Death.</p>
            <q>QUAE cauſas habent neceſſarias, prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videt Deus eventura neceſſario, quae verò à cauſis contingentibus pendent, contingentur eventura praevidet: Et ſic rerum contingentia ſeu mutabilitas abundè conſiſtere poſſit, cum divinae praeſcientiae infallibilitate; ſiquidem cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſas rerum non mutat, ſed quaſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ſuo loco relinquit. Porr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, nihil Deo prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teritum vel futurum, ſed omnia prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentia. Res igitur ratione Divinae prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientiae conſideratae, non ut praeteritae, non ut futurae, ſed ut praeſentes conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derandae ſunt. Veluti igitur res, quando ſunt, neceſſariò ſunt, nec ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men per hoc tollitur contingentia ſeu mutabilitas rerum; poterint enim ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter fieri antequam ita fierent: Ita Deo omnes res infallibiliter notae ſunt, ut
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:180513:36"/> pote ipſi praeſentes, quae tamen immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta ſcientiae divinae certitudo non tollit aut libertatem arbitrij aut rerum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingentiam.</q>
            <p>THERE is a far greater diſparity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Gods permiſſion, his preſcience, and his abſolute decreeing and appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Sin and final Miſery; than there is between one man's only permitting and ſeeing another man to ruin himſelf wilfully, tho he hath often told him the Danger, and given him ſuch Rules and Advice whereby he might have ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur'd himſelf from the leaſt peril;) and his forcing him to Deſtruction againſt his Will, againſt all Reaſon and Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
            <p>YET <hi>Calvin,</hi> and his rigid polemick Proſelytes contend, That all things, be they the moſt Criminal and Prodigious Acts, happen <hi>ex Dei nutu, conſilio, ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natione, &amp; impulſu.</hi> They endeavour in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed to palliate this by telling us, That Sin is meerly privative, and that the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:180513:37"/> Act is only from God, but not the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity of it; whereas Sin is poſitive, (as the Learned Dr. <hi>Pierce</hi> hath ſufficiently evinc'd;) and the Action and the Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of it cannot be disjoyn'd: and God doubtleſs upon no other account com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands us to avoid every evil Action, but becauſe the <hi>ratio formalis</hi> of Sin re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides in the action it ſelf.</p>
            <p>I ſhall tranſcribe ſome of their Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly Dreams, concerning Gods moſt Sacred Decrees and Actions; which may well make any ſober Chriſtian bluſh and tremble to read them.</p>
            <q>
               <p>HOMICIDIUM aut adulterium, quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Dei authoris, motoris ac impulſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris opus eſt, crimen non eſt; quantum autem hominis eſt, crimen ac ſcelus eſt.</p>
               <p>DEUS movet latronem ad occi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendum innocentem: <hi>Eſau</hi> quoque in infantia mori non potuit, quem divina
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:180513:37"/> providentia in hoc creavit, ut viveret at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> impiè viveret.</p>
               <p>DEUS poterit, ſi minus propri lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui velimus, dici aliquo modo aut ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium aut cauſa peccati.</p>
               <p>DEUS ita agit per mala inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, ut non tantum ſinat illa agere, nec tantum moderetur eventum; ſed etiam excitet, moveat, regat, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> hoc ipſo fine creet.</p>
               <p>MALA, quae agunt impij, ideo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunt, quia ad haec fuere deſtinati.</p>
               <p>DEUS homines ad adulteriam, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledicta, mendacia, ſanctè impellit, (ſanctè <hi>here is well plac'd;)</hi> &amp; ad peccata quae palam prohibet, occulta ratione incitat.</p>
               <p>HOMINEM non plus boni poſſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, quam facit, nec plus mali omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tere, quam omittit; imo Deum decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſſe
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:180513:38"/> apud ſe, quantum boni &amp; mali ab unoquoque praeſtari velit.</p>
               <p>HOMO ad peccandum à Deo coar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctatur.</p>
               <p>FATEMUR ac docemus impios om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ita a divina providentia regi, ut nihil aliud efficere queant, quam quod Deus aeterno ſuo &amp; immutabili conſilio decrevit.</p>
               <p>QUOD ais, iniquam &amp; hypocritam eſſe, ſi Deus per decretum ſuum nos ea facere nolit, quae ut faciamus praecipit; contraque facere non velit, quae nobis prohibet, falſum eſt.</p>
               <p>FRUSTRA de praeſcientia lis move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ubi conſtat ordinatione potius &amp; nutu omnia evenire. <hi>Cal. Inſt. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 23. <hi>ſ.</hi> 6.</p>
            </q>
            <p>THEIR ancient and firſt Maſters, the Gnoſticks and Manichees, could not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs themſelves in harſher Notions,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:180513:38"/> which make God not only to will and patronize Sin, but to impel and neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate men to it; which is directly oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to the Scriptures, which aſſert, That our Merciful Creator is ſo far from pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting or deſigning the leaſt Sin or Evil, that he prohibits and utterly abhors it, <hi>Zach.</hi> 8. 17. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5. 5. God, we concede, may deliver up without the leaſt inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, an impenitent Sinner to the obdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of his Heart, eſpecially when all that is done, is not by infuſing any ill quality into him, but by leaving him now to himſelf, who had ſo often held out againſt Gods gracious calls and invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations. So <hi>Pharaoh</hi> having hardned his own heart after the ſixth Judgment, and over and above fruſtrated <hi>Moſes</hi>'s ſpecial laſt warning: God then (but not before) is ſaid to harden his Heart, and would have deſtroyed him, but that he raiſed him up, or preſerv'd him alive, even for this purpoſe, to make the Divine Power more illuſtriouſly viſible in puniſhing ſuch a notorious Offendor, that would not be moved with ſo many Judgments
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:180513:39"/> of the Almighty. This indeed, <hi>viz. Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raohs</hi> obduration, was foretold by God from the firſt of his ſending <hi>Moſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> to him, <hi>Exod.</hi> 4. 21. But this foretelling it ſo ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is no argument that it was immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately done, but on the contrary his own hardning his own heart is alſo foretold, <hi>Exod.</hi> 3. 19. God ſhews Miracles and Signs before <hi>Pharaoh, Exod.</hi> 7. 10. and becauſe the Magicians did the like with their Inchantments, it follows <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s heart was hardned (not he) as if it were God) hardned <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s heart, but) <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh</hi>'s heart waxed hard, was ſtrong; or by an ordinary acception of <hi>Kal</hi> for <hi>Hithpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hel, Pharaoh</hi>'s heart hardned it ſelf. And ſo it follows, <hi>v.</hi> 14. the Lord ſaid unto <hi>Moſes, Pharaoh</hi>'s heart is waxen hard, he refuſeth to let the People go. But after the judgment, that of Boyls and Blains, <hi>Exod.</hi> 9. 10. then 'tis ſaid in a new Stile, the Lord hardned <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s heart <hi>v.</hi> 12. Which was the very time at firſt referr'd to by the prediction of God to <hi>Moſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IN like manner it happen'd to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:180513:39"/> Jews, who having reſiſted Chriſt after all the reſt of the Prophets, kill'd the Son after the Servants, and rejected the Apoſtles Preaching after Chriſts Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection: God then (but not before) gave them up to obduration, to become Veſſels of Wrath fitted for Deſtruction. And after this the great Jehovah, that is a moſt free and gracious Agent, and is not bound to this People or that, to primogeniture or the like, (as appears by the tipical Stories of <hi>Iſmael</hi> and <hi>Iſaac,</hi> of <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau,</hi> Rom. 9.) out of his gratuitous Mercy by the Preaching of the Goſpel, call'd and invited the Gentiles to Chriſtianity, to ſave them upon Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, without legal performances, upon internal and Evangelical, without exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and Moſaical obedience. (Peruſe the moſt elaborate and Orthodox Writings of the moſt Learned, Reverend, and Pious Dr. <hi>H. Hammond,</hi> concerning theſe and the like difficulties; and thou mayſt receive the cleareſt ſatisfaction.)</p>
            <p>BUT it could never enter into my
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:180513:40"/> Breaſt to imagine, that God from Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity did abſolutely decree the Fall, and the inevitable Perdition of the major part of mankind; or (as <hi>W. C.</hi> words it, <hi>pag.</hi> 13.) <hi>that God drew out Death</hi>'s <hi>Commiſſion before the Fall, but did not ſet his Hand and Seal to confirm it till after the Fall; and that in the counſel and purpoſe of God, Death was appointed unto men from Eternity:</hi> Which <hi>Calvin</hi> himſelf terms a dreadful and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Decree. <hi>Unde factum eſt, ut tot gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes unà cum liberis eorum infantibus aeternae morti involverat lapſus Adae abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> remedio, ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi quia Deo ita viſum eſt? Decretum quidem</hi> horribile <hi>fateor,</hi> Cal. Inſt. l. 3. c. 23 ſ. 7. 'Tis ſtrange I ſay, that ſome men ſhould be of ſuch ſour and moroſe (I had almoſt ſaid Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abolical) natures, as peremptorily to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, That God Created Souls purpoſely to damn them; or to uſe the Doctrine and the very words of <hi>J. M, That God takes as great glory and delight in damning of men, as he doth in ſaving of them.</hi> Monſtrous Divinity, and ſuch as is not to be found amongſt the ſottiſh <hi>Turks,</hi> or the rude <hi>Indians</hi> and <hi>Americans;</hi> and therefore I
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:180513:40"/> ſhould much wonder, did I not know what Charitable, and good-natur'd, and how free from Pride and Selfiſhneſs our Olivarian Speakers were; that Saints (as moſt ſhamefully they ſtiled one another) that liv'd in the <hi>Sun-ſhine of the Goſpel,</hi> ſhould yet contradict the moſt perſpicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Truths in it. For</p>
            <p>THE Sacred Bible, from <hi>Geneſis</hi> to the <hi>Revelations</hi> aſſerts, That the Divine Goodneſs, Clemency, Mercy, and Love, are exhibited to all Mankind really, upon Condition of Faith, Repentance, and amendment of Life, John 3, 16, 17. <hi>God ſo loved the World, that he gave his only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Son, that whoſoever believeth in him, ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſting Life. For God ſent not his Son to condemn the World, but that the World</hi> (all mankind) <hi>through him might be ſaved.</hi> Herein (Dr. <hi>Hammond.)</hi> hath Gods unſpeakable Love been expreſt to mankind, that he hath ſent his Eternal Son to aſſume our nature, and to teach and give Examples of Holy Life, and at laſt to dye for them, and
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:180513:41"/> riſe again, and aſcend the Heaven, all on this one Deſign, that every Perſon in the World, that ſhall receive and obey him, ſhall be reſcued from Eternal Death, and then made partaker of Eternal Life. For this my miſſion from God my Father was deſign'd all in Mercy and Charity, not to puniſh or condemn any man, but on purpoſe that all men might be reſcued from Puniſhment.</p>
            <p>MAT. 11. 28. <hi>Come unto me all ye that labor and are heavy laden, and I will give you reſt.</hi> Mar. 1. 15. <hi>Repent ye, and believe the Goſpel.</hi> Mat. 18. 11. <hi>The Son of man is come to ſave that which was loſt.</hi> Rom. 5. 8. <hi>God commendeth his love towards us, in that while we were yet Sinners Chriſt dyed for us.</hi> 1 Ep. St. Joh. 2. 1, 2. <hi>Jeſus Chriſt is the propiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation for our Sins; and not for ours only, but for the Sins of the whole World. Non ſolum</hi> (Bro.) <hi>pro peccatis Electorum, ſed ſingulorum hominum. Nam vox</hi> Mundi <hi>nuſpiam uſurpatur in literis ſacris pro ſclis electis.</hi> By the word <hi>World</hi> is never meant in the Sacred Writ only the Elect,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:180513:41"/> but either ſignifies the whole Compages conſiſting of the Heaven and Earth, or the whole race of mankind, both pious and wicked; or elſe the whole number of the wicked. And therefore 'tis very evident, That Chriſt came not only to ſave the Elect, that is, thoſe that have believed in him, and have thereby ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained Mercy; but alſo the Prophane, that have rejected his Counſels, and would not ſubmit to his eaſy Yoke and Golden Scepter.</p>
            <p>1 TIM. 1. 15. <hi>This is a Faithful ſaying, and worthy of all acceptation;</hi> (a Truth of an huge price, and fit to be the only Tradition or true Cabala among us Chriſtians, inſtead of all the Jewiſh Secrets and Miſteries;) <hi>that Jeſus Chriſt came into the World to ſave Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners:</hi> (to reſcue men out of their evil courſes, and upon reformation to obtain Pardon and Salvation for the greateſt Sinners, none excepted.) <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145. 8, 9. <hi>The Lord is gracious and full of compaſſion, ſlow to anger, and of great Mercy. The Lord is good to all, and his tender mercies</hi>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:180513:42"/> 
               <hi>are over all his Works.</hi> 'Tis the Title by which God was pleas'd to make known and proclaim himſelf to his People, <hi>Exod.</hi> 34. 6. <hi>The Lord, the Lord God, merciful and gracious,</hi> &amp;c. God is very forward and willing to pardon repentant Sinners, and not denying them that Grace, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding in Judgment againſt them, till he be provoked to it by great ingratitude and obdurations: and this Mercy of his is not incloſed to a few ſpecial Favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites of his, but inlarged and vouchſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed to all and every man in the World, upon the Title of his Fatherly Mercy to his Creatures, till by their impenitence perſiſted in, againſt his means of Grace, they render themſelves incapable of it. <hi>H. H.</hi> Paraph.</p>
            <p>GOD does ſeriouſly invite us to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>card our Sins, and tells us, That all our calamities iſſue from our own putrid Fountains, and not from the Divine will, or any Eternal and Inconditional Decree. For God cannot do or will Evil, <hi>viz. malum culpae</hi> the Evil of Sin, tho he may
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:180513:42"/> 
               <hi>malum paenae</hi> the evil of Puniſhment. <hi>Amos</hi> 3. 6. <hi>Shall there be evil in the City, and the Lord hath not done it?</hi> that is, the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Afflictions, which befal men for their impieties are from God. So. <hi>v.</hi> 1. <hi>I will puniſh you for your iniquities.</hi> God is the Author of no Evil, but that of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>Nam idem eſt</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Baſil) De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um aſserere peccati authorem, &amp; negare eſse Deum.</hi> 'Tis as impious to make God the Author of Sin, as 'tis to deny his very Being and Eſſence.</p>
            <p>PROV. 1. 23. <hi>Turn ye at my reproof.</hi> Ezek. 18. 32. <hi>I have no pleaſure in the Death (violent or eternal) of him that dyeth, wherefore turn your ſelves,</hi> for there is no fatal Remora, Sentence or Decree, or the leaſt defect on Gods part; <hi>and live ye.</hi> Mat. 23. 37. <hi>O Jeruſalem, how often would I (as I am God, as well as man) have gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thy Children together, and ye would not?</hi> Ye have oppos'd all the methods of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Wiſdom, refus'd all my invitations (ſaith the Holy Jeſus to the obſtinate
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:180513:43"/> Jews) tho never ſo frequent and paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>SED reſp. Calviniſtae, Chriſtum voluntate humana voluiſſe ſalutem Judaeorum, quia jux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta hanc voluntatem ei non erat notum, qui ex ijs convertendi eſſent: At voluntate diviná eorum ſalutem noluiſſe, alias converſi fuiſsent &amp; congregatt. Sed admiſſo hoc effngie, om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Chriſti promiſſiones, earumque veritas vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabitur in dubium. Quoties enim Chriſtus quidquam promiſiſse legitur, toties animi pendebit homo, an promiſerit voluntate divinâ an humanâ. Et fruſlra opponitur,</hi> Mat. 26. 39. <hi>Iſte enim locus hoc tantum evincit, volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem Chriſti humanam, diſtinctam fuiſſe a voluntate divini ſed ita ut illà vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntati divinae ſe ſemper ſubmiſerit, nec ab diverſum quidquam voluerit: Non enim abſolute petit ut tranſeat calix, ſed hac condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione, ſi poſſibile eſſet; &amp; additur ſtatim haec correctio, non quod ego volo, ſed quod tu vis, fiat. Cert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſimum eſt</hi> (ait Caſp. Er. Br.) <hi>Chriſtum ſecundum voluntatam tam divinam quam humanam voluiſse rebellium Judaeorum ſalutem: Nam verbum Dei diſertè docet, Chriſtum nihil in officio ſuo voluiſſe, dixiſse,</hi>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:180513:43"/> 
               <hi>docuiſse, quod non dixit, docuit, voluit, ad nutum, praeſcriptum, &amp; mandatum Patris.</hi> Joh. 5. 30. 8, 26, 28, 40. 14, 24.</p>
            <p>CAN any ſober and rational man then ſuppoſe, That God by any ſecret, fatal, and abſolute Decree willed and ordain'd, that the major part of this People, whom he had covenanted with, choſen, and own'd by many mercies and deliveran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſhould now neceſſarily continue blind, and oppoſe the means of grace of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd to them by his Son, their promiſed and long expected Meſſias? The holy Hiſtorian (Saint <hi>Luke</hi> the Phyſitian) tells us the contrary, <hi>Acts</hi> 3. 26. <hi>Unto you</hi> (the Jews) <hi>firſt God having raiſed up his Son Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, ſent him to bleſs you, in turning away e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one of you from his Iniquities.</hi> This doubtleſs then, <hi>viz.</hi> Gods eternal and immutable Decree, was not the cauſe of their rejection; but their own contuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and contempt of the Goſpel, <hi>Acts</hi> 13. 46. <hi>It was neceſsary that the word of God ſhould firſt have been Preached to you,</hi> (the Jews,) <hi>but ſeeing yee put it from you, (behave</hi>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:180513:44"/> 
               <hi>your ſelves ſo obſtinately and perverſly,) and judg your ſelves unworthy of eternal life,</hi> (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of receiving Benefit by the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel) <hi>lo, we turn to the Gentiles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>GOD, we know, tells us, That 'tis his Will that all men <hi>ſingula generum)</hi> ſhould be ſaved, and come to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the truth. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 4. <hi>That none ſhould periſh, but that all ſhould come to Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</hi> 2 Pet. 3. 9. <hi>and</hi> Rom. 11. 32. <hi>God hath concluded them all under unbelief, that he might have mercy upon all,</hi> (Jews and Gentiles which comprehend all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>SALUTEM omnium voluit Deus noſter clementiſſimus, non ſolum ſecundum volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ejus revelatam, externam ſeu ſigni; ſed etiam ſecundum voluntatem ejus occultam, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternam, &amp; beneplaciti. Nam volitio in Deo una eſt, ſicut eſsentia. Et voluntas ſigni dici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, quia eſt ſignum beneplaciti divini, ſeu quia ſignificat &amp; manifeſtat beneplacitum di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinum: At ſi latet beneplacitum divinum, tum etiam ſignum illius beneplaciti latet, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vata</hi>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:180513:44"/> 
               <hi>eadem proportione. Deinde, Quid eſt hipocritam &amp; ſimulatorem agere, ſi hoc non eſt? Verbo ſonoque exteriore ad vitam &amp; ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutem homines vocare atque invitare; ſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terno decreto eoque abſoluto atque immutabili eoſdem a vita &amp; ſalute arcere. Dei manda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt, ut ſermo noſter ſit ita &amp; ita; quo er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go jure dicere licebit, Deum aliud verbo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terius teſtari, aliud autem in corde ſuo clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum ſervare; in voluntate ſigni prae ſe ferre animum benevolum, in beneplacito autem ſuo habere animum inimicum. Notum eſt illud Homeri,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>—'Tis an odious thing to let the tongue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict the heart, to ſpeak fair and intend the contrary.</p>
            <p>THE five Virgins, mentioned <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. had they not been fooliſh, that is, care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and improvident, might have had as free admiſſion into the Bridegrooms Chamber, as the five wiſe or provident. Hence the Prodigal Son, that made his Felicity expire with his Eſtate, and by his Travels had gain'd nothing but the knowledge of iniquity and penury; yet no
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:180513:45"/> ſooner returns and leaves his miſdemea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, but he receives a paternal embrace. For Gods arms were, are, and ever will be open to encloſe the meaneſt Converts, and will give them ſuch a ſufficiency of Grace, both internal and external, which bringeth Salvation, and hath appeared unto all men, <hi>Titus</hi> 2. 11. which, if they reſiſt not, will at laſt be found to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and effectual: For ſufficient and effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacious grace are not two different ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of Grace, but one and the ſame; and the Divine Grace is term'd either this or that, only <hi>ab eventu,</hi> as 'tis improv'd by us.</p>
            <p>PRAY conſider, Should we laſh a Cripple for halting, or having clog'd and fetter'd a Slave, require him to run a race; ſhould we exhort the Dumb to ſpeak, and the Deaf to her, or condemn and deride one born Blind, becauſe he cannot diſtinguiſh colours; this would argue the higheſt Phrenſie and Fury. And can we then be ſo ſtupid and irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious to imagine, that the great God of Heaven, that is full of Wiſdom, Equity,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:180513:45"/> and Love, would invite (and upon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſal torment to Eternity) thoſe men to walk in his Paths, and to behold the Light of the Goſpel, whom he himſelf had ſhackled and blinded by a fatal and inevitable Decree? Far be it from us Chriſtians to judge thus of a Deity, that hath proclaim'd, and prov'd himſelf to be more merciful to the Sons of men, than the moſt indulgent Parent can be to his only Child. And ſurely 'twould be no ſmall Wonder, if a Father that hath ten Sons of equal merit, ſhould take two of them into his Favour and Protection; and expoſe the reſt to the mercileſs and impetuous rage of Lyons and Tygers. And if you ſhould ask him the reaſon of this his inhumanity, he could anſwer nothing but <hi>Sic volo ſic jubeo—</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have no more reaſon to object and delate againſt my eight Children, that I have rejected, than againſt the two that I have cheriſh't and embrac'd; I might, if I would have preſerv'd all from perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but 'twas my will and pleaſure on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:180513:46"/> and nothing elſe, that the far great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er number, maugre their ſad cries and expoſtulations, ſhould fall and periſh to eternity. This doubtleſs is no Criteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or ſure ſign of a Paternal affection; but an evident Demonſtration of one of the moſt prodigious Monſters in nature. I need not apply it. In ſhort,</p>
            <p>THESE crude and fatal Aſſertions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned, concerning the Divine decrees and appointments; cannot be palliated, ſweeten'd, or well digeſted, by their pleading that God is under no Law, which (ſaith a judicious Author) is a very Lawleſs and unreaſonable pretext; for the everlaſting rectitude of his ſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs nature, is more than any external Law: and pray what can Truth and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice do, but what is holy and juſt? Or by their ſubtile diſtinguiſhing <hi>inter jus Dei abſolutum &amp; ordinatum, inter reproba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem &amp; damnationem, inter reprobationem privativam &amp; poſitivam, inter praeteritionem &amp; damnationem.</hi> For he that avers Gods abſolute will and pleaſure to be the Sole
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:180513:46"/> Cauſe of preterition and reprobation, may with the ſame confidence affirm it to be the prime (if not ſole) cauſe of damnation. <hi>Tantum diſcriminis eſt inter praeteritionem &amp; damnationem, quantum dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferentiae intercedit inter haec duo; inferre mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem &amp; nolle vitam alicui continuare, abſque quâ vitae continuatione mors neceſsario ſequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi> Whereas the Scriptures (the only Rule of our Faith, unleſs we will admit of Enthuſiaſm,) aſſure us, That 'tis mens crying Sins, their contumacy, impeniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and incredulity, <hi>(&amp; non abſolutum Dei in homines &amp; creaturas jus, non Dei be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neplacitum, ſeu abſoluta ejus voluntas,</hi> that are the real Cauſes both of preterition, reprobation, and damnation. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 18, 19. <hi>Joh.</hi> 6. 40. <hi>Mark</hi> 16. 16.</p>
            <p>THE Conſequences and reſults of theſe Calviniſtical Dreams, and fatal Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, are very ſad, diſmal, and nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous; ſome whereof I ſhall nominate, and then conclude.</p>
            <p n="1">1. THEY confine and limit Gods
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:180513:47"/> power, and make him a neceſſary Agent; for he cannot puniſh or deſtroy the moſt blaſphemous and bloodieſt men, before their appointed time; nor ſhorten or extend the days of the virtuous.</p>
            <p n="2">2. THEY derogate from Gods good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, mercy, and juſtice; for what great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er tyrany and injuſtice, than to judge men to endleſs flames, without any intu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ition of faith or incredulity, of obedience or diſobedience? For ſurely 'tis not ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, (as ſome Hypochondriacks fancy,) but the higheſt cruelty to make men mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, that thereby he might take an occaſion of ſhewing juſtice.</p>
            <p n="3">3. THEY contradict Gods Veracity; for what more falſe and perfidious than to ſay and ſwear, That he willeth not the Death, but the ſafety and converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe, whom, notwithſtanding by an immutable and irreſiſtable Decree, he hath deſigned to eternal Death and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:180513:47"/> 4. THEY make God with <hi>Marcion, Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Magus,</hi> the <hi>Manechees,</hi> the prime and principal Author of all the Crimes, and horrid Villanies acted under the Sun. <hi>Cum enim Cauſa ſuperior &amp; omnipotens, ita moveat &amp; determinet cauſam inferiorem &amp; impotentiorem, ut ea ſic mota ac determinata non poſſit non peccare; ſtupidus ſit oportet, qui non animadvertat conſtitui hac ratione Deum peccati cauſam, &amp; quidem propriam &amp; prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. THEY render Chriſts Nativity, his Holy Life, his bitter Death, his glorious Reſurrection and Aſcention, and his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual Interceſſion for us at the Throne of Grace; yea all Preaching and Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the Sacraments, and all juſt and vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Actions, to be vain, uſeleſs, and ineffectual: For to what purpoſe all this? if 'tis abſolutely decreed from Eternity, who ſhall be ſav'd, and who ſhall be damn'd, <hi>ſine fide praeviſa, ſine praeviſis ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus. Praedeſtinationem vocamus aeternum Dei decretum, quo apud ſe conſtitutum ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buit quid de unoquoque homine fieri vellet.</hi>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:180513:48"/> 
               <hi>Non enim pari conditione creantur omnes, ſed aliis vita aeterna, aliis damnatio aeterna praeor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinatur.</hi> Calv. Inſt. lib. 3. cap. 31. ſ. 5.</p>
            <p n="6">6. THEY lead men, eſpecially the Vulgar, and thoſe of the weaker Sex, (as we have often known,) either into Preſumption or Deſpair; ſome poor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded Souls think the Gate of Mercy ſhut, when 'tis wide open, and become melancholy and diſtracted; and others, tho rebels, traytors, hereticks, and ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks, grow proud and cenſorious, and dream that it will fall open to them (tho precious and witneſſing People, Gods Cupboard of Plate, as in modeſty they ſtile themſelves) without the leaſt knock or ſtriving.</p>
            <p>AND Laſtly, They are inlets and broad roads to ſecurity and all licenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, if I ſhall live, I ſhall live; if I ſhall be ſav'd, I ſhall be ſav'd; do what I will: if I ſhall dye, I ſhall dye; if I ſhall be damn'd, I ſhall be damn'd; do what I can: for the Decree and Sentence either
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:180513:48"/> of Life or Death is eternal, is immutable, paſt and irrevocable. Therefore <hi>Ede, bibe, lude—</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THESE prodigious Effects and ſad conſequences being clear and demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, 'tis prudence to ſtop our ears, and (if I may uſe <hi>W. C</hi>'s. martial phraſe,) to <hi>buckle our ſelves</hi> againſt all ſuch fatal O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions and wild Whimſies, that are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to reaſon, and the very nature of a Deity, to the purport and Oeconomy both of the Law and the Goſpel: What is aſſerted in this ſmall Tract, is, I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume, conſonant to both, to Gods word, and to that Light <hi>(viz.</hi> Reaſon) he has ſeated in us to judge and ballance things by. Here is no Popery, no Pelagianiſme or Semi-Pelagianiſme, which ſome cry for want of arguments, as a ſufficient confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. For we firmly believe, that 'tis by Gods grace and providence that we live, move, and have our Being in this World; and by which, by the merits of the Holy Jeſus we expect Salvation in the Other. We ſtedfaſtly believe the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:180513:49"/> Apoſtles Symbole; that God is true and juſt in all his ways, and righteous in all his dealings; that his ſecret Will is not oppoſite in the leaſt punctilio to his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed; and that he that believeth and is baptized, that ſincerely repents of his former ſins, and forſakes them ſhall be ſaved, ſhall receive plenary pardon, and upon perſeverance to the end, eternal bliſs; but he, and he only that ſtands out obſtinately and impenitently ſhall be damn'd. Our extravagant thoughts, and fooliſh confiding and depending on our abſolute Election, may be a ſnare and ſtratagem to deceive and ruine us; but our ſerious and hearty Perſwaſions, That the Divine Decrees and appointments are conditional; ſo that we are hereby mov'd and allur'd to come to God with a filial love and fear, and incited to duty and action, to real piety and honeſty, to do as we would be done by, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends both what the Law and the Prophets hath taught us; This belief, I am ſure, can never delude us, no Decree can baffle this: For Godlineſs, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 8.
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:180513:49"/> hath the Promiſe of the life that now is, and of that which is to come.</p>
            <p>THIS may ſuffice to demonſtrate to all conſidering men, that are not biaſſed by intereſt, prejudice, or prepoſſeſſions, That the preſent State of the Body, and the future State of the Soul, are not limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and determined by any fatal, abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute, inconditional, immutable, and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptory Decree; but that both Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and Soul by the Divine grace and providence may (if we be not defective in our own Duty) be infinitely bleſſed and happy.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:180513:50"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:180513:50"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Catalogue of ſome Books lately Printed for</hi> Tho. Baſſet <hi>at the</hi> George <hi>in</hi> Fleet-ſtreet.</head>
            <list>
               <item>DR. <hi>Littletons</hi> Dictionary, <hi>Engliſh-Latine</hi> and <hi>Latine-Engliſh,</hi> in 4to.</item>
               <item>Bp. <hi>Wilkins</hi> of the Principles and Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes of Natural Religion, 8vo.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Sparks</hi> Devotions on the Feaſts and Faſts of the Church, 8vo.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Wanley</hi> of <hi>Coventry</hi> his Hiſtory of Man, wherein by many thouſands of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples is ſhewed what Man hath been from the firſt Ages of the World to theſe times, in reſpect of his Body, Senſes, Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, Affections, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in Folio.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Allingtons</hi> Reformed Samaritan: a Viſitation Sermon, Preached in <hi>Coventry,</hi> to which is annexed a Diſcourſe about the Neceſſity and Expediency of Set forms in 4to.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Meritons</hi> Hiſtory of <hi>England</hi> in 120.</item>
               <item>The 12. and <hi>13th</hi> parts of Sr. <hi>Edw. Cooks</hi> Reports, in Folio.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Browns</hi> Religio Medici, in 8vo.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:180513:51"/>
               <item> Sr. <hi>Thomas Herberts</hi> Travels, in Folio.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pools</hi> Engliſh Parnaſſus, or a Help to <hi>Engliſh</hi> Poeſie, in 8vo,</item>
               <item>Sr. <hi>Roger Manleys</hi> Ruſſian Impoſtor, or Hiſtory of <hi>Muſcovy,</hi> in 8vo.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pharmacopoeia Londinenſis,</hi> newly alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and Enlarged throughout the whole work, according to the preſent Practice: by the Colledge of Phyſicians, <hi>London.</hi> In Folio and 24to</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pharamond,</hi> or the Hiſtory of <hi>France,</hi> a fam'd Romance in 12 parts, in Folio.</item>
               <item>Sr. <hi>John Vaughan,</hi> late Chief Juſtice of the Common-Pleas, his Reports and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, in Folio.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Mieges</hi> New Dictionary, French and Engliſh, and Engliſh-French, in 4to.</item>
               <item>The Hiſtory of <hi>France,</hi> Containing all the Memorable Actions in <hi>France,</hi> and other Neighbouring Nations, in Folio.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Daltons</hi> Juſtice of Peace, newly enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, Folio.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hudibras,</hi> the firſt and ſecond part, in 8vo.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Swinburns</hi> Treatiſe of Wills and Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, in 4to.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:180513:51"/>
               <item> 
                  <hi>Doctrina Placitandi,</hi> or the Art of Plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, in 4to.</item>
               <item>The Hiſtory of <hi>Don Quixot,</hi> Folio.</item>
               <item>Judg <hi>Hales</hi> of the Primitive origination of Mankind, Folio.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:180513:52"/>
            <head>Advertiſement<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </head>
            <list>
               <head>Now in the Preſs.</head>
               <item>THE ten Volumes of Year Books, with Tables to the whole, and references<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> never before Printed.</item>
               <item>And alſo <hi>Guillims</hi> Heraldry, with many Additions</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:180513:52"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
